<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>This Week in Rust</title><link href="https://this-week-in-rust.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://this-week-in-rust.github.io/categories/rust/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://this-week-in-rust.github.io/</id><updated>2014-07-15T15:40:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>State of Rust 0.11.0</title><link href="https://this-week-in-rust.github.io/blog/2014/07/15/state-of-rust-0.11.0/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-15T15:40:00-04:00</updated><author><name>TWiR Contributors</name></author><id>tag:this-week-in-rust.github.io,2014-07-15:blog/2014/07/15/state-of-rust-0.11.0/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello and welcome to the &lt;em&gt;State of Rust&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rust-lang.org/"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt; is a systems
language pursuing the trifecta: safe, concurrent, and fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past 6 months since the last one of these updates was
written, Rust has evolved significantly: the standard library was
refactored to make Rust more convenient to use in embedded or
bare-metal platforms, the language has been greatly simplified (moving
most pointer types into libraries) and the package ecosystem has been
thriving under a new package manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-rust-project"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Rust Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is now its &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/rust-lang/"&gt;own organization&lt;/a&gt; on GitHub! This reflects that Rust
is a major project with its own community and culture, and not simply
another project under the Mozilla umbrella. Additionally, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/rust-lang/meeting-minutes"&gt;meeting
minutes&lt;/a&gt; now live in that organization, if you're interested in
watching those. We have also introduced a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://internals.rust-lang.org/"&gt;Discourse forum&lt;/a&gt; for
discussing the design and implementation of Rust and its standard
libraries.  An &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rfcs/"&gt;RFC process&lt;/a&gt; has been introduced for proposing
changes to the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rust-lang.org/install.html"&gt;official nightlies&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rust-lang.org/rustup.sh"&gt;script that installs them&lt;/a&gt;, which
provides a dead-simple way to install Rust without waiting over half an hour
for a build. Our &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://play.rust-lang.org/"&gt;online sandbox&lt;/a&gt; also provides instant gratification, and
all doc examples are runnable in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on from meta-topics, many changes have happened in the language
itself. Many features have been removed.  These and other less-major
changes make the language simpler, more consistent, and more powerful.
An incomplete list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;do&lt;/tt&gt; expressions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Freeze&lt;/tt&gt; kind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;priv&lt;/tt&gt; keyword (everything is private-by-default)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All variations of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;#64;&lt;/tt&gt;-pointers. They are replaced by the library
type, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Gc&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, which shares many of the same problems &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;#64;&lt;/tt&gt; did,
implementation-wise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All variations of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;~&lt;/tt&gt;-pointers. They are replaced by the library
types, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Box&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Vec&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt; for &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;~T&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;~[T]&lt;/tt&gt;
respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dereferencing is now overloadable, via the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Deref&lt;/tt&gt; and
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;DerefMut&lt;/tt&gt; types. This makes creating and using smart pointers
much more painless!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &amp;quot;placement new&amp;quot;, or more accurately, &amp;quot;placement box&amp;quot; feature has
been added. This replaces &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;~expr&lt;/tt&gt; and will be extensible to user
types. &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;box 42i&lt;/tt&gt; has type &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Box&amp;lt;int&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;. This feature is still
baking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The libraries have also seen a lot of love. Rather than having a
single, monolithic &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libextra&lt;/tt&gt;, there are now multiple more focused
libraries. A list is available on our fancy new &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://doc.rust-lang.org/#libraries"&gt;documentation index
page&lt;/a&gt;. Of particular note, a huge amount of effort was spent
splitting &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libstd&lt;/tt&gt; itself into smaller pieces. There is a (rather
large!) subset, which lives in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libcore&lt;/tt&gt; that uses no dynamic
allocation or other such runtime features. &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libcore&lt;/tt&gt; is suitable for
use in embedded, bare-metal, and other resource constrained
environments. &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;libstd&lt;/tt&gt; still presents a unified interface to all of
the individual pieces, and is the stable entry point to the entire
standard library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compiler has also grown a plugin system, that allows for
user-defined syntax extensions, lint passes, and exportable macros.
This is not well documented yet, but the new &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://doc.rust-lang.org/regex/"&gt;regex crate&lt;/a&gt; takes
great advantage of this to provide compile-time checked regular
expressions that can compile &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; into Rust code, rather than
always running them in a virtual machine at runtime or requiring a
complex JIT compiler for good performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Klabnik has been hired on a 6 month contract to improve our
documentation. He has been busy filling in examples and writing our &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://doc.rust-lang.org/guide.html"&gt;new
guide&lt;/a&gt;. Our documentation will be vastly improved as time goes on, in
preparation for the big 1.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-rust-ecosystem"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Rust Ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most marked change in Rust is its community. It is growing
faster than I could have anticipated. There are many projects being
undertaken by groups of people who aren't also working on the compiler
or standard library. This is a significant shift from the past, where
trying to do a project in Rust almost forced you to improve Rust or
abandon it. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://zinc.rs/"&gt;Zinc&lt;/a&gt; project is building a bare-metal ARM stack aiming at
writing a completely safe RTOS toolkit. It uses a loadable syntax
extension to describe the hardware features of a particular
hardware platform.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.piston.rs/"&gt;Piston&lt;/a&gt; project is a growing community of game developers
building libraries and an engine to make developing interactive
graphical applications painless and safe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ironframework.io/"&gt;Iron&lt;/a&gt; project has created a Rack-inspired web framework that
allows easily composable &amp;quot;middleware&amp;quot; to stack and build a robust
web application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many other smaller libraries and projects the community is
undertaking, however these three represent major areas that Rust is
great for and are the largest (in terms of developers/maturity) in
their respective spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making things even better, the official package manager, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://crates.io/"&gt;Cargo&lt;/a&gt;, has
finally been released! It is only in alpha, but is maturing quickly.
The magnificent &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rust-ci.org/"&gt;Rust CI&lt;/a&gt; is tracking which repositories have Cargo
support. Uptake has been rapid, which bodes very well for its
continued success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="looking-forward-is-rust-ready-yet"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looking Forward (&amp;quot;Is Rust ready yet?&amp;quot;)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; ready yet. It still has a few more release cycles before 1.0. In
particular, the &amp;quot;unboxed closure&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;dynamically sized types&amp;quot; work is not
yet complete. There are also many minor changes to improve ergonomics in the
pipeline. That said, it is becoming more stable, and many major features are
complete. If you want to, give it a spin, and let us know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>The State of Rust 0.9</title><link href="https://this-week-in-rust.github.io/blog/2014/01/12/the-state-of-rust-09/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-12T21:13:00-05:00</updated><author><name>TWiR Contributors</name></author><id>tag:this-week-in-rust.github.io,2014-01-12:blog/2014/01/12/the-state-of-rust-09/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.rust-lang.org/"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt; is a systems language pursuing the trifecta:
safe, concurrent, and fast. This is my post-mortem of the past 3 months, the
current status of Rust, and its future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h1 id="compiler"&gt;Compiler&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compiler saw a fair bit of work this release cycle. Some polish has gone
into &lt;code&gt;mut&lt;/code&gt; in patterns. For example, &lt;code&gt;let (mut x, y) = foo();&lt;/code&gt; now works as
expected. We now have "feature gates", or feature flags, that let us mark
certain features as either deprecated or experimental and subject to change.
&lt;code&gt;@mut&lt;/code&gt; has been removed. Slice representation has been optimized (we now store
number of elements, not number of bytes). Soundness bugs have been fixed, and
some bugs in our name resolution have been patched up. We have a dead code
warning, stability annotations, crate introspection, and lots more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of all that, we also have support for static linking and LTO. Compiler
performance has further improved. From the 112ms compiling &lt;code&gt;fn main() { }&lt;/code&gt; in
0.8, we now do 91ms with static linking (the default) and 68ms for dynamic
linking (&lt;code&gt;-Z prefer-dynamic&lt;/code&gt;). Our debuginfo is in a much better state. The
entire codebase (compiler + standard library + tools) compiles with it, and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/servo/"&gt;Servo&lt;/a&gt; compiles with it by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="runtime"&gt;Runtime&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The runtime has seen tons of work this release. &lt;code&gt;std::io&lt;/code&gt; has been swapped
over to the new runtime, which is written entirely in Rust. We now support
both 1:1 and M:N threading models, their respective runtimes supplied by
"libnative" and "libgreen". libgreen (the "old new runtime") has seen some
performance improvements. Chris Morgan reports that the scalability of his
&lt;a href="https://github.com/chris-morgan/rust-http/"&gt;rust-http&lt;/a&gt; benchmarks has
improved from 1.25x to 1.75x from 1 to 8 concurrent request handlers. On my
machine, using libnative gives an impressive performance boost, pushing us
ahead of go's performance (graph below). libnative has yet to see any optimization work.
David Renshaw reports roughly a 2x performance increase on his &lt;a href="http://dwrensha.github.io/capnproto-rust/2013/11/16/benchmark.html"&gt;capn proto
benchmark&lt;/a&gt;
when using libnative for I/O.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://docs.google.com/a/octayn.net/spreadsheet/oimg?key=0ArjzeYh7LqL2dENRREdRbDljajR4LWt1RlozM2YyY0E&amp;oid=1&amp;zx=xnqmqanhavt" /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(This would be interactive if you had JavaScript enabled)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="//ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/static/modules/gviz/1.0/chart.js"&gt; {"dataSourceUrl":"//docs.google.com/a/octayn.net/spreadsheet/tq?key=0ArjzeYh7LqL2dENRREdRbDljajR4LWt1RlozM2YyY0E&amp;transpose=0&amp;headers=1&amp;range=A1%3AE6&amp;gid=0&amp;pub=1","options":{"titleTextStyle":{"bold":true,"color":"#000","fontSize":16},"series":{"0":{"errorBars":{"errorType":"none","magnitude":10}}},"animation":{"duration":500},"width":600,"hAxis":{"title":"Concurrency (\"threads\")","useFormatFromData":true,"minValue":null,"viewWindowMode":null,"viewWindow":null,"maxValue":null},"vAxes":[{"useFormatFromData":true,"title":"Requests / second","minorGridlines":{"count":"4"},"minValue":null,"gridlines":{"count":"5"},"logScale":false,"viewWindow":{"max":null,"min":null},"maxValue":null},{"useFormatFromData":true,"minValue":null,"logScale":false,"viewWindow":{"max":null,"min":null},"maxValue":null}],"booleanRole":"certainty","title":"rust-http comparison benchmark","height":371,"domainAxis":{"direction":1},"legend":"right","focusTarget":"series","useFirstColumnAsDomain":true,"isStacked":false,"tooltip":{"trigger":"none"}},"state":{},"view":{"columns":[{"calc":"stringify","type":"string","sourceColumn":0},1,2,3,4]},"isDefaultVisualization":false,"chartType":"ColumnChart","chartName":"Chart 1"} &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can run the benchmarks yourself. &lt;code&gt;cd comparisons; python run.py&lt;/code&gt;. You'll
need to build rust-http first (&lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;), and have go, nodejs, and ab (apache
bench) installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="documentation"&gt;Documentation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our documentation hasn't been in the best state in the past. It still isn't
where it should be, but &lt;a href="http://static.rust-lang.org/doc/master/index.html"&gt;they have been
reorganized&lt;/a&gt;, on top of
seeing the usual work. We're in the process of moving all of the documentation
from the wiki onto that site, to make it easier to find and search. Steve
Klabnik gave a &lt;a href="https://air.mozilla.org/rust-meetup-december-2013/"&gt;critical but very constructive
presentation&lt;/a&gt; at the Bay
Area meetup about what we are doing wrong and how we can improve. At the same
meetup, Chris Morgan talked about the technologies we use in our documentation
stack. In the long run, the consensus seems to be that reStructuredText and
Sphinx are they way forward. Thanks to the rustdoc rewrite, it will be able to
have first-class status as a documentation backend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-future"&gt;The Future&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 0.10, we have &lt;a href="http://smallcultfollowing.com/babysteps/blog/2014/01/05/dst-take-5/"&gt;Dynamically Sized Types
(DST)&lt;/a&gt; to
look forward to, as well as the removal of &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt; pointers. &lt;code&gt;box&lt;/code&gt;, aka "placement
new", along with smart pointer sugar (overloadable dereferencing/borrowing),
should also be in by then. We may also see an actual garbage collector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="is-rust-ready-yet"&gt;Is Rust Ready Yet?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope. It still has some work to do. 1.0 is estimated before the end of 2014,
though that may slip depending on how things land. An early estimate puts the
release over the summer! We still need a robust package manager. We now have
&lt;a href="http://rust-ci.org/"&gt;rust-ci&lt;/a&gt;, which makes it easy to keep code up to date,
and know if a library is up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The breaking changes, especially language changes, are slowing down, besides
bug fixes. The standard library is also starting to shake itself out, though
it still has a lot of work before they will be stable. There are currently two
known uses of Rust in production: &lt;a href="http://www.tilde.io/"&gt;Tilde&lt;/a&gt; is using it in
&lt;a href="https://www.skylight.io/"&gt;Skylight&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://opendns.com"&gt;OpenDNS&lt;/a&gt; is
using it for &lt;a href="http://labs.umbrella.com/2013/10/04/zeromq-helping-us-block-malicious-domains/"&gt;real-time data
processing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been a good release, and the next will be even better. Want to get
involved? &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/rust/wiki/Note-guide-for-new-contributors"&gt;We love
contributions&lt;/a&gt;.
Want to follow development? I post a &lt;a href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/categories/this-week-in-rust/"&gt;weekly
newsletter&lt;/a&gt;
summarizing the important changes. There is also a
&lt;a href="http://reddit.com/r/rust"&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt;. Here's to an awesome 0.10!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The State of Rust 0.8</title><link href="https://this-week-in-rust.github.io/blog/2013/10/06/the-state-of-rust-08/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-10-06T20:32:00-04:00</updated><author><name>TWiR Contributors</name></author><id>tag:this-week-in-rust.github.io,2013-10-06:blog/2013/10/06/the-state-of-rust-08/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another 3 months, another release. This is the first release that I've
witnessed in its entirety! This is a summary of Rust: its compiler,
libraries, documentation, and community. (&lt;a href="http://rust-lang.org"&gt;What is
Rust?&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h1 id="compiler"&gt;Compiler&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compiler is faring well. It received a lot of attention in compile speed,
although memory usage regressed significantly. It is now mostly fixed in
master. Time compiling &lt;code&gt;fn main() { }&lt;/code&gt; went from 172ms to 112ms on my box.
When compiling programs of any significance, the gap is much larger. There's
also been some thought put into parallelizing rustc. Michael Woerister's GSoC
project was debuginfo, and it's almost in a fully-working state. As of 0.8,
it's not completely baked -- libstd can't be compiled with it, and stepping
through code isn't perfect -- but it's a huge step forward, and he created an
extensive testsuite, so it shouldn't regress. The pretty printer hasn't seen
much improvement. Default methods, one of the major things Michael Sullivan
worked on over the summer, are in a much better state. If there are any
remaining bugs in them, I haven't seen them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="iterators"&gt;Iterators&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iterators are hugely improved for 0.8. The &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loop syntax now uses the
Iterator trait. Additionally, most uses of vector iterators now compile to the
exact same code that indexing or iteration would in C or C++, including the
ability to be vectorized. Additionally, they now use default methods instead
of extension implementations. A bunch of other extensions to Iterator were
added, such as DoubleEndedIterator and RandomAccessIterator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="documentation"&gt;Documentation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation is in a much better state than it was 3 months ago. The new
rustdoc was started and finished. I started it, and Alex Crichton really
polished and finished it the last two weeks before the release. The API
documentation is now navigable, and one can actually see the relationship
between various types. A bunch of work also went into the tutorials, yielding
three new documents: error handling and conditions, iterators and containers,
and rustpkg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="rustpkg"&gt;&lt;code&gt;rustpkg&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rustpkg continues to advance. Tim put out the call for community involvement,
and it's getting significant traction in actual libraries. There are still a
few kinks when using it for development, but when just fetching and building
dependencies, it works very well. Servo is porting its whole mini-ecosystem
over to rustpkg, uncovering bunches of problems and deficiencies in the
process. If you're interested in helping out with Rust, rustpkg is a major
area. Tim is also super nice, and will happily help you get into the codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="libraries"&gt;Libraries&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is slowly accreting more and more useful libraries: mostly coming from
the gamedev community, but sometimes other useful things as well. The
new runtime has completely replaced the old, a significant step forward for
Rust's maturity. &lt;code&gt;rust-http&lt;/code&gt; is making some really nice strides, as well as
the opengl bindings. The standard libraries are becoming nicer to use.
&lt;code&gt;std::run&lt;/code&gt;, in particular, stands out to me as something that's quite easy to
use, and &lt;code&gt;std::str&lt;/code&gt; saw a lot of work making it more correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-future"&gt;The Future&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great release cycle, and I think the next one will be even better.
Alex Crichton was hired as a full-time Rust developer, and he has been doing a
lot of important work that just would have taken a while to happen otherwise.
I'm very optimistic about this release, much more so than 0.7. I think we
might be able to hit milestone 1 for 0.9 or 0.10, though that's just
speculation on my part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="is-rust-ready"&gt;Is Rust Ready?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. Rust is approaching maturity, but it isn't there yet. There are still
backwards-incompatible changes being made to try and get to milestone 2.  The
major things that come to mind are closure reform and privacy overhaul (which
is being worked on in master &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/rust/pull/9735"&gt;right
now&lt;/a&gt;). Additionally, people in the
gamedev community are starting to &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/rust/comments/1nxs1h/the_state_of_rust_08/ccnb8ya"&gt;hit walls with the type
system&lt;/a&gt;.
Those probably won't be fixed in the time leading up to 1.0, but this is also
speculation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experimenting with Rust is becoming more viable as time goes on, but using it
in production is a bad idea, especially if "low maintenance" is at all
valuable.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The State of Rust 0.7</title><link href="https://this-week-in-rust.github.io/blog/2013/07/05/the-state-of-rust-07/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-05T09:51:00-04:00</updated><author><name>TWiR Contributors</name></author><id>tag:this-week-in-rust.github.io,2013-07-05:blog/2013/07/05/the-state-of-rust-07/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Given the influx of newcomers from the 0.7 release, I thought it'd be a good
idea to summarize the condition of Rust, its libraries, and its documentation.
bstrie said it best I think, "basically, any question of the form 'is there a
reason for this stupid and terrible thing' is 'no, sorry, we're working on
it'&amp;nbsp;".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h1 id="iterators"&gt;Iterators&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;External iterators are a main feature of the 0.7 release, and there is ongoing
work to remove all of the library features that use internal iterators. Most
of them are gone, and there are few uses of internal iterators. However, they
are clunky to use. The &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loop semantics are going to change from internal
iteration to external iteration, but they are still internal iteration right
now, which means the &lt;code&gt;advance&lt;/code&gt; adaptor is necessary for most uses of
iterators. Additionally, the &lt;code&gt;iter()&lt;/code&gt; helper function is necessary to actually
return an iterator. This will be obviated by an &lt;code&gt;Iterable&lt;/code&gt; trait that many
things will hopefully implement. Due to
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/rust/issues/5898"&gt;5898&lt;/a&gt;, many methods are oddly
named or have an underscore appended (ie, &lt;code&gt;transform&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code&gt;position_&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;position&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="io"&gt;IO&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IO has been a bit of a losing proposition since at least 0.2. The interface is
very primitive and inefficient. It requires using &lt;code&gt;@Trait&lt;/code&gt; objects (&lt;code&gt;@Reader&lt;/code&gt;
/ &lt;code&gt;@Writer&lt;/code&gt;). It's also very undocumented. But the situation isn't going to
improve much because all of that code is getting torn out when brson/the
interns finish their work on the new runtime. On the plus side, we'll have
shiny new IO when they're done! If you want to contribute, there's plenty of
work to be done in this area:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/rust/issues/6169"&gt;issue 6169&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/rust/issues/6850"&gt;issue 6850&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/rust/issues/4419"&gt;issue 4419&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://mail.mozilla.org/pipermail/rust-dev/2013-May/004305.html"&gt;brson's status report for June&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="compiler"&gt;Compiler&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compiler is still buggy and inefficient. Lots of things work, but lots of
things don't. There's still some resolve bugs (the one mentioned above, as
well as some others, and perpetually poor error messages), default methods
don't work, debuginfo is incomplete, the compiler has quadratic codegen when
using &lt;code&gt;match&lt;/code&gt;, so on and so forth. There's a lot of work to be done here but
it's not easy. I'm writing a series about the compiler that should help new
contributors get started and grok how it all fits together. The only thing
making Rust usable right now is LLVM's fantastic optimization. Our no-opt
builds run slower than our opt builds under Valgrind. Ponder that for a
minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="rustpkg"&gt;&lt;code&gt;rustpkg&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;rustpkg is still heavily in-progress and unfinished. It's usable, but not
everything is implemented, and the documentation is incomplete. It's rather
unintuitive to use right now, but it does work! Read the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/rust/blob/master/doc/rustpkg.md"&gt;manual&lt;/a&gt; carefully
if you want to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="documentation"&gt;Documentation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documentation is poor. &lt;code&gt;rustdoc&lt;/code&gt; is really bad, which doesn't help. I'm
working on a new rustdoc (&lt;a href="http://rustlog.octayn.net"&gt;I log my progress
here&lt;/a&gt;), but it won't be ready for some weeks. Lots
of things are undocumented or near impossible to find because of how bad
&lt;code&gt;rustdoc&lt;/code&gt; is. The tutorials need lots of work, and a guided tour of the
libraries would be nice, as well as a "Rust By Example," showing how to
accomplish common goals. These aren't really hard to do, it's just that nobody
has done them yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="libraries"&gt;Libraries&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are few robust libraries or bindings to libraries, for anything, besides
what is in std/extra. There's the stuff servo uses (glfw, skia, sdl), and an
opengl binding somewhere, but beyond that, you're on your own. The
&lt;a href="https://github.com/crabtw/rust-bindgen"&gt;rust-bindgen&lt;/a&gt; tool can help with
wrapping a C library. There is no GUI library available yet, no real
networking. It's easy to wrap a C library, you just need to be careful with
your &lt;code&gt;unsafe&lt;/code&gt; blocks. Once again, these things aren't hard, they just haven't
been done yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-future"&gt;The future&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically everything is heavily WIP, but it's constantly improving. We always
need more contributors, ask in IRC if you're interested. Rust 0.7 is pre-alpha
quality, IMO. It would be silly to use Rust for something important, but don't
let that stop you from trying to do something ambitious. If you feel Rust is
still too young to get involved, but you want to track its progress, I write
&lt;a href="http://cmr.github.io/blog/categories/this-week-in-rust/"&gt;This Week in Rust&lt;/a&gt;,
which is an easy way to track our progress. 1.0 is tentatively planned for
first-quarter 2014, last I heard, and I don't think that is out of reach. 1.0
corresponds to "maturity #2" at the absolute minimum (the maturiy levels are
listed &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/rust/issues/milestones"&gt;as milestones&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But don't be discouraged. It was far worse before! Rust is in a good position,
it's just not quite all there yet. This post may seem pessimistic, but the
progress Rust has made is astonishing. Here's to a wonderful 0.8!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="some-links"&gt;Some links&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/rust/"&gt;Rust subreddit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://mail.mozilla.org/listinfo/rust-dev"&gt;Mailing list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.gmane.org/gmane.comp.lang.rust.devel"&gt;Mailing list archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://chat.mibbit.com/?server=irc.mozilla.org&amp;amp;channel=%23rust"&gt;IRC
  Channel&lt;/a&gt;
  (it's &lt;code&gt;#rust&lt;/code&gt; on irc.mozilla.org)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary></entry></feed>